Hi, this is Matt Baker. Recently, I've
been getting a lot of comments on my
line of succession to the British throne
video asking about this guy. As you've
probably heard by now, Andrew, who until
recently was known as his royal
highness, Prince Andrew, the Duke of
York, is now just plain old Andrew
Windsor Mountbatton due to his alleged
sex crimes and other illegal activity
related to his friendship with Jeffrey
Epstein. But the big question is, is
Andrew still in the line of succession?
Well, unfortunately, the answer is yes.
So, in today's video, I'm going to
explain why this is. In addition to
explaining the process involved in
unprincing a prince and unduking a duke.
So, when it comes to the rules relating
to British royals, some decisions are
based on what's called royal
prerogative, whereas others are based on
acts of parliament. Let's start with the
issue of who gets to be a prince or
princess. This one is based on royal
prerogative which means that the
decision is up to the monarch and the
monarch alone. Most of the time the
rules set forth by previous monarchs
simply continue to get followed.
However, if the current monarch, in this
case Charles III, wants to make any
changes, he has the ability to do so
without getting permission from anyone
else. So currently the main document
that determines who gets to be a prince
or princess is this one known as the
letters patent of 1917 signed by King
George to V. It states that the children
of any sovereign of these realms shall
have and at all times hold and enjoy the
style title or attribute of royal
highness with their titular dignity of
prince or princess. So this means that
Andrew at birth was automatically a
prince because he was born the child of
a sovereign. And basically someone in
his position gets to keep that title
unless at some later point a sovereign
decides to remove it which rarely
happens. But in this case it did.
Initially Ander himself released a
statement saying that he simply wouldn't
use the titles prince or his royal
highness. But then just 2 weeks later,
Charles III issued an official letters
patent stamped with the great seal of
the realm, which legally took away those
titles from his brother. So this now
overrules the letter patent of 1917
and means that Andrew is no longer a
prince. It also means that he now uses
the surname Mount Batten Windsor. You
see, princes don't need last names, but
non-p princes do. And when it comes to
the royal family of the UK, the surname
used by anyone who is not a king, queen,
prince, or princess is Mount Batton
Windsor. Mount Batton being the house
name of Prince Philillip and Windsor
being the house name of Queen Elizabeth.
Now, take note that this series of
events is very different from the ones
involving Prince Harry and the two
children of Prince Edward. In Harry's
case, the Queen issued a statement in
2020 saying that Harry and Megan would
no longer be using the styles his or her
royal highness. However, she did not
issue an official letters patent and
therefore it doesn't carry the same
weight. It's more of a FYI, here's what
we've decided to do sort of thing. She
also didn't take away Harry's title of
prince. In the case of James and Louise,
a similar thing happened prior to their
birth. The queen issued a statement
saying that any children of Edward and
Sophie would be styled as the children
of an earl and thus would not use the
titles prince or princess. To this day,
they have never used them. But again,
this was not done in the form of a
letters patent and therefore legally
James or Louise could at some future
date opt to use them. In other words,
the method used by King Charles to
unprince Andrew was the strongest method
available to him. It's something we have
not seen since World War I when two
British princes had their statuses
removed for siding with Germany. Next
up, I want to discuss the title Duke of
York. But first, I want to tell you
about the website and app that I use to
keep up with the latest news. It's
called Ground News. And what it does is
pull headlines from hundreds of
different sources from all over the
world, whether they're newspapers,
podcasts, or websites. It then groups
them by political bias, so that for
every breaking story, you get to look at
things from multiple angles. For
example, Ground News recently gathered
hundreds of articles about Trump's plan
to pull 700 immigration officers from
Minneapolis. Left-leaning sources framed
the ICE operation there as being a
violent raid that led to the killings of
two US citizens, whereas right-leaning
sources called the operation a victory
over sanctuary policies. Of course, the
best thing about ground news is the
charts, such as this one showing the
bias distribution, or this one showing
which sources are the most factual based
on third party rankings, or this one
showing what percentage of the sources
are independently owned or owned by the
government or big business. So, don't
wait. Subscribe now by going to
ground.news/charts
or by using the link in the description
or pinned comment. If you use that
address or link, you will get 40% off
unlimited access to their Vantage plan.
Again, that's ground.news/charts.
Let's now discuss Andrew's title, Duke
of York, as well as his lesser titles,
Earl of Inesse and Baron Killerly. These
three titles are hereditary purigages
and were given to him on the day that he
got married. Now the thing with purges
like this is that they can be given
based on royal prerogative but in order
to be taken away it requires an act of
parliament. So in this case king Charles
was unable to simply declare that his
brother is no longer the Duke of York.
However he did find a sort of middle
solution without having to ask the
parliament to get involved. You see, in
the UK, the chancellor is required to
maintain a role of the purage, which is
basically a list of everyone in the UK
who has a fancy title. And the law says
two important things about this list.
First, it says that any pure not entered
on the role shall not be addressed or
referred to by any title attaching to
his puridge. And second, it says that
the chancellor may take such steps and
do such acts as he considers expedient
to preparing and keeping the role. So
what King Charles did was issue a letter
directing the chancellor to remove
Andrew from the role, which she did. So
what this means is that Andrew can no
longer be referred to by his periage
titles. However, technically he does
still hold them, which brings me to the
line of succession. Again, in this case,
the only way to remove someone from the
line of succession is through an act of
parliament. And here it gets even more
complicated because the British monarch
is not only the monarch of the United
Kingdom, but also of 14 other countries.
So, in order to remove Andrew from the
line of succession, 15 different
parliaments would have to pass 15
different acts. At the moment, that
seems unlikely to happen because since
the chances of Andrew ever inheriting
the throne are pretty much zero, most
politicians do not see it as a high
priority. Now, a few additional things
that do fall under royal prerogative are
who gets to be called a knight belonging
to organizations such as the Order of
the Guarder and the Royal Victorian
Order, as well as certain honorary
military titles. In these cases, King
Charles was able to simply strip his
brother of those honors. Then, of
course, there are certain things that
require neither a decision by the king
nor a decision by the parliament, such
as whether or not your own daughters
want to speak to you anymore. In
Eujenei's case, she has publicly stated
that she has cut off contact with both
her father and her mother. I also know
of at least one school that has changed
their name. You see, when I was growing
up in Dartmouth, Nova Scotia, we had a
school called Prince Andrew High School,
which several of my best friends
attended. It was named that because it
opened in 1960, the year that Andrew was
born. Well, in 2022, the school board
voted to change the name to Woodlon High
School. Okay, there's one more thing to
mention regarding Andrew and that is the
role of counselor of state which is a
list of people who are appointed to act
on behalf of the monarch during times of
incapacity. According to law, the spouse
of the monarch as well as the first four
adults in the line of succession are
automatically counselors of state. So
that would be Queen Camila, Prince
William, Prince Harry, Andrew, and
Princess Beatric. Out of this list, only
two are working royals. So just prior to
her death, the queen actually asked the
parliament to amend the law to add
Prince Edward and Princess Anne as well.
Thus, the list still contains four
working royals. So if anything comes up,
Andrew in particular can be avoided.
Now, I should also mention that the
Windsor are not the only royal family
with a connection to Jeffrey Epstein.
Also appearing in the Epstein files is
the crowned princess of Norway, Meta
Marit. In fact, her name appears over
1,000 times. Plus, her son from a
previous relationship, Marius Borg Hoy,
is currently facing 38 criminal charges,
including four counts of rape. So while
none of this impacts the line of
succession to the Norwegian throne,
there have been questions over whether
or not Metamarit should serve as the
future queen consort. Now obviously the
most important thing when it comes to
the whole Epstein situation is not
understanding how it has impacted royal
families, but understanding how it has
impacted the victims. Above all else, we
should be listening to them and to those
who have suffered similar abuse so that
we can perhaps help prevent these sorts
of things from happening to other
children. But since that topic is
outside of my wheelhouse, I want to end
by introducing you to someone who deals
with these issues more headon. My wife
Charlotte. Charlotte has worked as both
a college instructor and journalist and
is herself a survivor of child sex
trafficking. Through her involvement in
peer-to-peer counseling and
anti-trafficking activism, she has
talked with victims of both Jeffrey
Epstein and of the Russian oligarchy and
therefore understands the darkness of
what the former prince was involved in
better than most. She has both a well-
readad blog and now a YouTube channel.
So, if you want to learn more, I'll drop
links to those in the description.
Thanks for watching.